Okay, בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf is
דף ס"ג daf samech gimmel and we start with the next משנה.
mishnah.
And this משנה, mishnah, okay, and we start with the next משנה
mishnah and we now are moving on to מנחות menachot which is
actually quite interesting because we have a whole מסכת masechet about מנחות,
menachot,
but it's just provides a little bit of a contrast, right? The
previous פרק perek was all about the different קרבנות korbanot and the
major theme there was that the קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim were slaughtered
in the north as opposed to the קדשים קלים, kodshei kalim, the
קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim were eaten only in the עזרה azarah in
the temple courtyard, you know, courtyard the לפנים מן הקלעים lifnim min
hake'laim and the קדשים קלים kodshei kalim the שלמים shlamim was eaten
in all of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. And then that was last פרק perek
and then this פרק perek began like with a little variation about
that. The question about what happens if you שחט shacht קדשי קדשים
kodshei kodashim at the top of the מזבח, mizbe'ach, okay, but so
that's still in the aftermath like sort of a wrapping up stuff
from the previous פרק, perek, right? And then this משנה mishnah here
speaks about a מנחה mincha which as I said there's an entire
מסכת masechet about, but it does it provides a little bit of
a contrast, right, to
the and a little surprising based on what we might have thought
because a מנחה mincha classically is קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodashim, it's only
eaten by male כהנים, kohanim, it's only eaten in the courtyard of
the עזרה, azarah, it's only eaten in the עזרה azarah and the
courtyard of the temple, and let's take a look what the משנה
mishnah says about where you actually do the act of קמיצה. kemitzah.
So the מנחה mincha here, the משנה mishnah here begins on the
top of ס"ג. samech gimmel. מנחות היו נקמצות בכל מקום בעזרה. Menachot
hayu nikmatzot bechol makom ba'azarah. You could do the קמיצה kemitzah which
was parallel to the שחיטה, shechitah, you could do it anywhere in
the courtyard, it does it did not have to be only in
the north, even though in all other ways it's similar to a
קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodashim, but this does not have a limit a
designated place about where the act of קמיצה kemitzah is done. ונאכלות
לפנים מן הקלעים לזכרי כהונה בכל מאכל יום ולילה עד חצות. Vene'echalot
lifnim min hake'laim lezichrei kehuna bechol ma'achal yom valailah ad chatzot.
And the rest of it is like word for word what we
say by קדשי קדשים. kodshei kodashim. It's eaten by male כהנים kohanim
in the עזרה azarah the day and the following night until midnight
and so on. So the point of saying this here was to
show this contrast about where the קמיצה kemitzah is done. So let's
take a look at the גמרא. gemara. אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi
Elazar, מנחה שנקמצה בהיכל כשירה. mincha shenikmetza baheichal kesheira. So before getting
to this question of where you know that it could be anywhere,
we actually start by another חידוש chiddush which is saying that let's
say you actually did it in the היכל heichal itself, right where
there's the, you know, שלחן shulchan and the מנורה, menorah, so what
would be the story? You could ask the same question about like
שלמים, shlamim, right? When it says any place in the עזרה, azarah,
does it include inside the actual היכל heichal itself? So by a
מנחה mincha the answer is yes.
שכן מצינו בסידור בזיכין. Shechen matzinu besiddur bazichin.
When think about the act about when they would for the לחם
הפנים. lechem hapanim. The לחם הפנים lechem hapanim on the שלחן shulchan
inside the היכל heichal was a type of a מנחה. mincha. What
was the קמיצה kemitzah there? What was the thing offered to the
altar that allowed the bread to be eaten? Well there was no
קמיצה, kemitzah, there was no taking of the flour of the bread
itself, but there was the taking of those two little like spoons
of frankincense from the from the base of the table, from the
from the top of the table I should say, and that was
put on the outer altar. So that was parallel to the קמיצה,
kemitzah, it's something to be burnt on the outer altar in order
to allow the מנחה mincha to be eaten. And that act of
taking was an act that was done in the היכל. heichal.
He would of course he would take it from the היכל heichal
because that's where it was.
Right, okay, so you could sort of say אי אפשר משאי אפשר
ee efshar mishe'ee efshar type of a thing. That's true, that is
true, so Michael makes a good point there, you didn't have an
option, right, so places where you have an option maybe you're not
allowed. All right, but anyway the גמרא gemara is saying is that
from there we can infer that מנחות menachot are appropriate acts done
to מנחה mincha are appropriate even in the היכל. heichal. מתיב רבי
ירמיה, Mativ Rabbi Yirmiyah,
and רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah challenged this. וקמץ משם ממקום שרגלי הזר
עומדות.
Vekamat misham mimakom sheraglei
hazar omdot.
So it says it says that, you know, the person brings the
מנחה mincha to the בית המקדש beit hamikdash and it says then
the כהן kohen goes and he takes from the מנחה mincha that
the person brought he does the קמיצה, kemitzah, וקמץ משם במלוא קמצו
מסולת המנחה ומשמנה על כל לבונתה והקטיר המזבחה. Vekamat misham bimlo kumtzo
misoles hamincha umishaman veal kol levonatan vehiktir hamizbeachah. Okay,
so therefore it says only until the way this is being read,
so the קמיצה kemitzah can only happen up to the place where
the זר, zar, the non-כהן kohen can go. And that therefore where
how far can the non-כהן kohen go? Normally we say it's the
first eleven אמות amot into the עזרה azarah is called עזרת ישראל
ezrat yisrael and after that it's עזרת כהנים. ezrat kohanim. But technically
speaking a ישראל yisrael could go further in as well assuming he
was טהור. tahor. But he could not go to the space between
the אולם ulam and the מזבח mizbe'ach and he certainly could not
go into the אולם ulam into the היכל. heichal. So this he
says seems that the קמיצה kemitzah has to happen only in the
zone in which in theory a ישראל yisrael could go. Isn't that
what this is telling you? So בן בתירה אומר Ben Beteira omer
מניין שקמץ בשמאל יחזיר ויקמוץ בימין. minayin shekamat bismol yachzir veyikmot biyamin.
Before we get to answer that question here's the end of the
ברייתא. braita. מניין שקמץ בשמאל שיחזיר ויקמוץ בימין. Minayin shekamat bismol sheyachzir
veyikmot biyamin.
How do you know if you do a קמיצה kemitzah with your
left hand you could put it back in and do it again
with your right hand, right? It's like, you know, we've had that
before; if you mess it up, can you do it again? If
you mess up the שחיטה, shechitoh, you can't do it again unless
you're like, you know, אלישע Elisha and you're going to do a
little תחיית המתים techiyas hamaysim or something. But other things, right, if
you, if you, you know, walk the blood with your wrong hand,
can you go back and do it again with your right? If
you, you know, if you did some of the blood with your,
threw it on the altar if there's leftover blood, can you do
it again? So by the קמיצה, kmitzoh, if you did it with
your left hand, can you put it back in and go ahead
and do it with the right hand? So how do you know
that's true? This is parenthetical, but this is what he learns from
the פסוק: posuk: תלמוד לומר משם, Talmud lomar mishom, דקמץ משם, dekomatz
mishom, from there. ממקום שקמץ כבר. Mimokom shekomatz kvar.
So from the place where the קמיצה kmitzoh had already taken place,
you take the קמיצה kmitzoh again. I'm not exactly sure how we
get משם mishom meaning that it's, it's a redo, but okay. So
he says he doesn't learn from there the issue about where the
זר zar can go, he learns from there the הלכה halachoh that
you get, you can do a redo if you need to. But
for the point that you can do it where the זר zar
can go, that seems to say not, not the היכל. heichal.
Which means that that means that a קמיצה kmitzoh with the wrong
hand is nothing, right?
Because as we said, in י"ד, yud daled, that's what we said
and we had similar questions.
But
then that mean, you know, you could still say that there's something
wrong with the part that you took, but now you're saying it's
not.
It's like, right, and it's like a הלכה halachoh and whatever and
we've had this before, we can go back and compare it to
earlier discussions in the פרק. perek. But back to our question: so
therefore, what do you do with this? This sounds like it's only
limited up to the place a זר zar can go. So איכא
דאמרי הוא מותיב לה והוא מפרק לה. Ika d'amri hu moviv lah
v'hu mefarek lah. Some say רב ירמיה Rav Yirmiyah asked the question
and he said, "Wait, wait, I know an answer to my, I
can give the answer to this question that I myself just asked."
איכא דאמרי אמר ליה רבי עקיבא, Ika d'amri amar leh Rabbi Akiva,
or some have רבי יעקב Rabbi Yaakov because רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
wouldn't exactly be responding to רב ירמיה Rav Yirmiyah talking about תחיית
המתים. techiyas hamaysim. Anyway, אמר ליה רבי יעקב לרב ירמיה בר תחליפא
אסברא לך, Amar leh Rabbi Yaakov l'Rav Yirmiyah bar Tachlifa asbera lach,
let me explain it to you, how why this is not a
question, because this ברייתא brayso that says until where the זר zar
can go: לא נצרכה אלא להכשיר כל הזר כולו. Lo nitzrecha ela
l'hachshir kol hazar kulo. Okay, where it says where a זר zar
can go is coming not to tell you, it's not a limit,
it's an expansion. So you read it, "Oh, only as far as
a זר zar can go, not into the היכל." heichal. That's not
the point. The point is anywhere a זר zar can go, which
means, and this is going back to our משנה mishnah because our
משנה mishnah is, wait a minute, this is just קדשי קדשים, kodshei
kodoshim, everything's קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodoshim, why don't you have to do
it in the north? How do you know a מנחה minchah doesn't
have to be in the north? And the answer to that question
is וקמץ משם. v'komatz mishom. Wherever the זר zar brings it, that's
where the כהן kohen takes it. And maybe you could say even
better, normally of course a זר zar wouldn't be bringing it to
the north of the altar. I mean, again, in theory maybe he
could go there. So therefore, the fact that it emphasizes that the
קמיצה kmitzoh is done right at the point where the זר zar
brings it up to, okay, is a clear indic, indicator that it
does not have to be in the north. And that's what we
learn from that to allow any place other than any place even
if it's not the north of the altar. It is not coming
to restrict and to say it can't be in the היכל. heichal.
That's not its point. Okay. לא נצרכה אלא להכשיר כל הזר כולו.
Lo nitzrecha ela l'hachshir kol hazar kulo. סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salca daitach
amina,
I mean I would have thought to say הואיל ועולה קדשי קדשים
ומנחה קדשי קדשים, Ho'il v'olah kodshei kodoshim u'minchah kodshei kodoshim, and both
קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodoshim, מה עולה טעונה צפון, Mah olah te'unah tzafon,
the same way the עולה olah is the north of the altar,
אף מנחה טעונה צפון, af minchah te'unah tzafon,
so the מנחה minchah is the north of the altar. So therefore
it needed to tell me not the way. So גמרא Gemara says,
"One minute, why would I have made that comparison? I don't need
a פסוק posuk to tell me that. I don't have a good
basis to say north. You want to make a comparison to עולה?
olah? עולה olah is different. מה לעולה שכן כליל, Mah l'olah shekein
kalil, an עולה olah is totally burnt. All right, מה חטאת, mah
chatas, fine, I would've learned it from a חטאת. chatas. But some
מנחה minchah are totally burnt. That's true, but you don't do קמיצה
kmitzoh with them. מה לחטאת שכן מכפרת, Mah l'chatas shekein mechaperes,
no, I wouldn't have learned it from a חטאת, chatas, that atones.
מנחה Minchah doesn't atone. אלא מהיכא דקרי ליה רחמנא חטאת, Ela meheicha
d'karei lei rachmana chatas,
fine, all right, fine.
ואשם, v'asham, okay, well let's learn it from an אשם. asham.
No, מה לאשם שכן מין דמים, Mah l'asham shekein min domim, no,
at least אשם, asham, it's true, but at least אשם asham is,
is blood." Maybe there's something unique to slaughtering and blood. So I
don't need a פסוק posuk to say it doesn't have to be
the north. The תורה Torah never said north, and it's not similar
enough to all the animal sacrifices. It's not an animal sacrifice. Okay.
וכן לכולהו מה לכולהו שכן מין דמים. v'chein l'culhu mah l'culhu shekein
min domim. אלא איצטריך, Ela itztarich, now
here's why I would've thought so. You're right, just to make an
analogy to the animal sacrifices would not have been strong enough to
compel me to say the north and I wouldn't have needed a
פסוק posuk to say otherwise. So what, but here's why I would've
said it. אלא סלקא דעתך אמינא, Ela salca daitach amina, I would
have thought הואיל וכתיב והגישה אל המזבח והרים ממנו בקמצו, ho'il u'chtiv
v'higishah el hamizbeiach v'heirim mimenu bikmitzo,
the גמרא Gemara is giving up easily, maybe Mykoff is being a
little too easy because there are פסוקים pesukim that link מנחה minchah
to the other things, so maybe we should have pressed our case.
But גמרא Gemara is not saying that. גמרא Gemara is going to
say fine, you know what, I wouldn't have had a הוה אמינא
hava amina of north. Let's leave the animal sacrifices alone. Let's just
focus internal within מנחות, minchos, מנחות. minchos. But even within מנחות, minchos,
I would have thought that it had to be a more specific
place where you're going to do the קמיצה. kmitzoh. Why is that?
Because here's what it says. אלא סלקא דעתך אמינא הואיל וכתיב והגישה
אל המזבח, Ela salca daitach amina ho'il u'chtiv v'higishah el hamizbeiach, you
touch it to the altar, והרים ממנו בקמצו, v'heirim mimenu bikmitzo, and
afterwards it says you take the קמיצה. kmitzoh. מה הגשה בקרן דרומית
מערבית, Mah hagashah b'keren dromis maarovis, we're going to learn in a
minute that where it has to touch the altar is the south-west...
to be a more specific place where you're going to do the
קמיצה. kmitza. Why is that? Because here's what it says. הא כתיב
והגישה אל המזבח, ha ketiv vehigisha el hamizbeach, you touch it to
the altar, והרים ממנו בקמצו, veyarem mimenu bekumtzo, and afterwards it says
you take the קמיצה. kmitza. מה הגשה בקרן דרומית מערבית, mah hagasha
bekeren dromit maaravit, as we're going to learn in a minute that
where it has to touch the altar is the southwest corner. So
because that's true and I'll just tell you for a second why,
okay, because again, here's your מקדש, mikdash, here's your altar, right, here's
your north, south, east, west,
speak.
I knew you'd have that be coming up today.
What, me drawing the picture?
Yes, that picture.
That picture. Of course. Okay, anyway, so, so we're going to say
in a minute that there's two פסוקים psukim that speaks about where
you bring the מנחה. mincha. One says לפני השם lifnei Hashem and
the other says על פני המזבח. al pnei hamizbeach. So the פני
המזבח, pnei hamizbeach, if you assume this is the face because this
is where you hit when you go up and it's לפני השם,
lifnei Hashem, what's that going to get you? And לפני השם lifnei
Hashem is facing the היכל, heichal, that's going to get you the
southwest corner. Okay, how do you know it's a corner? Well, because
you have to get both the לפני השם lifnei Hashem and the
על פני המזבח. al pnei hamizbeach. So therefore, so therefore that's where
you're going to touch it. So I might think if that's where
you touch it and then right afterwards the verse says do the
קמיצה, kmitza, that you have to do the קמיצה kmitza right at
that place. And so you know, go ahead do the קמיצה kmitza
wherever you want. Okay, I mean it's convenient to do it there
but you don't have to.
So I want to say מה הגשה בקרן דרומית מערבית אף קמיצה
בקרן דרומית מערבית. mah hagasha bekeren dromit maaravit af kmitza bekeren dromit
maaravit. קמשמע לן, kamashma lan, so there I learn from where it
says וקמץ משם, vekamatz misham, wherever the זר zar brings it, that
it doesn't have to be there. So again, וקמץ משם vekamatz misham
is not coming to tell you only where the זר zar brings
it, meaning to exclude the היכל, heichal, it's coming to tell you
anywhere the זר zar brings it to allow you to do the
קמיצה kmitza anywhere in the עזרה. azarah. קמשמע לן. kamashma lan. אמר
רבי יוחנן. Amar Rabbi Yochanan. Okay, so now we've established that you
can do the what do you call it, the מנחה mincha inside
the היכל. heichal. Now we're going to ask, well, okay, let's ask
the next obvious question, what about שלמים? shlamim? שלמים shlamim can be
anywhere
in
the עזרה, azarah, can they be in the היכל? heichal? This is
similar by the way, I want to just point out, think about
the issue about can you שחט shacht an עולה olah at the
top of the מזבח? mizbeach? Does it have to be to the
north of the מזבח mizbeach or can it be on the מזבח
mizbeach itself? So here, this can be שחט shachted anywhere, so if
it can be שחט shachted anywhere in the עזרה, azarah, does that
include even in the היכל? heichal? Okay, or maybe sometimes too close
is actually not a good thing.
All right, so it would seem to make sense that while קמיצה
kmitza could happen in the היכל, heichal, שחיטה shchita shouldn't.
You don't want blood all around your beautiful היכל. heichal. Yeah, I
would agree.
Well, other than the fact that, you know, you're also doing blood
on some time on יום כיפור Yom Kippur there, you know,
it's a little bit more add to an actual slaughterhouse in your
היכל. heichal. Okay, so that's a good point. Okay, so let's take
a look. אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, שלמים ששחטן בהיכל, shlamim
sheshchatan baheichal, if you slaughtered them in the היכל, heichal, כשרים. ksherim.
Look at that, it is כשר. kosher. שנאמר ושחטו פתח אהל מועד,
shenemar veshachato petach
ohel moed, you normally, the normal way it's described is by the
opening of the אהל מועד, ohel moed, and we had a discussion
how anywhere in the עזרה azarah is the opening, they opened up
all these doors. So now, if it could be by the opening
of אהל מועד, ohel moed, so it's in reference to the אהל
מועד, ohel moed, so if it's always in reference to the אהל
מועד, ohel moed, ולא יהיה טפל חמור מן העיקר, velo yihiyeh tafel
chamur min haikar, so something secondary, reference to the אהל מועד, ohel
moed, should not be stronger than in the אהל מועד ohel moed
itself. Okay, I don't know exactly if that's true, we're going to
see the גמרא Gemara question it that I think I told you
last time when we had a similar discussion about שחטינג shchating at
the top of the altar rather than to the north of the
altar. About how I was once, once playing miniature golf and they
had a contest like the next, you know, everybody line up, hit
the ball the closest to getting into the hole gets a free
game. So I got it into the hole. I didn't get the
free game. Why? It's only the closest to the hole, not actually
in the hole!
Anyway, okay. So the גמרא Gemara says, so this is to anyway,
that's the question. Okay, so מיתיבי, meitivei, רבי יהודה בן בתירה אומר,
Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira omer, I'm going to challenge this. רבי יהודה
בן בתירה Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira says, מניין שאם הקיפו עובדי כוכבים
את כל העזרה, minayin sheim hikifu ovdei kochavim et kol haazarah, there
you are, they were on the eighth of אב, Av, they were
surrounding the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, they were surrounding the עזרה azarah
and everybody was forced, they were actually in the temple courtyard and
the only place to go, it's really like, you know, the idea
of a sanctuary, right? So the only place to go is in
the עזרה azarah itself, at least that had walls, maybe they were
able to keep them out. And there they were, they were banging
at the gates and you had to eat your קרבן, korban, or
maybe you were doing it because, you know, you had to survive.
Anyway, so מניין שהקיפו עובדי כוכבים את כל העזרה, minayin shehikifu ovdei
kochavim et kol haazarah, שהכהנים נכנסים לשם ואוכלים שם קדשי
קדשים,
shehakohanim nichnasim lesham veochlim sham kodshei
kodashim, how do you know you could eat your קדשי קדשים kodshei
kodashim in the עזרה azarah proper? Not only in the courtyard but
actually in the, actually not the עזרה, azarah, excuse me, in the,
yeah, excuse me, in the now meaning they're surrounding the עזרה, azarah,
okay, they're filling the עזרה, azarah, and you're going into there meaning
into the היכל. heichal. Okay, so how do you know when they're
in the עזרה azarah surrounding you and you're in the היכל, heichal,
how do you know the כהנים kohanim can eat their קדשי קדשים
kodshei kodashim in the היכל heichal proper?
בקודש הקדשים תאכלנו, bakodesh hakodashim tochelenu, that's this week's פרשה.
parsha. תלמוד לומר בקודש הקדשים תאכלנו. talmud lomar bakodesh hakodashim tochelenu. That's
a head's up over there. Thank you, Michael. Okay, so look, it
says explicitly, הוה אמינא, hava amina, so certainly so it's not only
the courtyard, even in the היכל. heichal. Now why is that a
question? Because there at least you got a פסוק. pasuk. So you
got a פסוק pasuk by מנחה, mincha, we got a פסוק pasuk
by eating the meat, but you need a פסוק pasuk for. פסוקים
psukim that you don't just make an argument that oh if it
works in the עזרה azara it certainly works in the היכל, heichal,
you don't make a קל וחומר kal v'chomer like that. Okay, ואמאי,
ve'amai, why did we need a פסוק? pasuk? נימא, neima, בחצר אהל
מועד יאכלוה, bachatzer ohel moed yochluha, ולא יהא קל וחומר מיני ומינה?
v'lo yehei kal v'chomer minei u'meina? Why not just say if you
can eat it in the courtyard, you can eat it in the
אהל מועד? ohel moed? So clearly you don't make a קל וחומר.
kal v'chomer. It's not obvious if you could do it in the
courtyard you could do it in the היכל. heichal. So if that's
true by the eating of the meat, also by the שחיטה shechita
you can't make a קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. So the גמרא Gemara
says הכי השתא? hachi hashta? Wait, you can't compare. It's easier to
make a קל וחומר kal v'chomer in one case than the other.
The opposite what Benzy said. Why?
Because התם עבודה דאדם עובד במקום רבו אמרינן לא יהא קל וחומר
מיני ומינה. hatam avoda d'adam oved bimkom rabbo amrinan lo yehei kal
v'chomer minei u'meina. When it comes to שחיטה, shechita, that's a way
of serving God. So serving God, if you can do it when
you're more removed to God, you can do it when you're closer.
Although of course like sometimes the way you want people to serve
you is to take care of the stuff out of your presence.
I want to go to the butcher and have my chicken all
nice packaged in cellophane or whatever so I don't even know that
it comes from an animal, okay, and I don't want to see
the person שוחט-ing shochet it in my presence. But anyway our argument
is that, you know, that's actually, you know, the point about like
who wants all that blood in the היכל. heichal. But no, the
גמרא Gemara saying if we just step back and abstract it, it's
serving God, so if you can do it a little bit more
removed, you can do it closer. So that was our קל וחומר.
kal v'chomer. We would not have said the same about the eating
of the meat, even though it's more dignified, but we would not
have had a קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. Okay, אכילה דאין
אדם אוכל במקום רבו,
achila d'ein
adam ochel bimkom rabbo, but you don't eat in the presence of
your master, ולא יהא קל וחומר מיני ומינה v'lo yehei kal v'chomer
minei u'meina we would not have said. So we need a פסוק.
pasuk. Right, so we needed a פסוק. pasuk. So a פסוק pasuk
taught us by the מנחה mincha because you do it by the
שולחן, shulchan, that you do that act, although that's dignified, it taught
us by the eating, although it's not an עבודה, avoda, you didn't
have a קל וחומר, kal v'chomer, but nevertheless the פסוק pasuk tells
us you're allowed to do it. And then, and this is really
ironic, the קל וחומר, kal v'chomer, which of course can be questioned,
is used to tell us you can do what I think we
all can agree is the most like, you know, seems the most
inappropriate: taking a whole cow and slaughtering it inside the היכל. heichal.
So you can abstract it and say yes it's an עבודה avoda
to be done more inside, but clearly it does not seem to
be appropriate for the location for the setting.
So when we say שלמים shlamim that you're allowed to eat and
slaughter in
any קרבן, korban, really.
Correct. Well but שלמים shlamim and anything else you couldn't because it
had to be the north of the מזבח. mizbeach. So it's only,
so that's why we use the example of שלמים. shlamim. שלמים shlamim
was the only thing that you could slaughter other than the north
of the מזבח, mizbeach, and that can be even in the היכל.
heichal.
Wait, I'm sorry, wait, so it means so if you're אשם asham
you can't שחט?
shacht? Correct, because that's not to the north of the מזבח. mizbeach.
It's only שלמים. shlamim.
But you can still eat them.
Right. The point is, correct, anything that could be done anywhere in
the
עזרה: azara: קמיצה, kmitza, שחיטת קדשים קלים, shchitat kodashim kalim, and אכילת
קדשי קדשים achilat kodshei kodashim can be done in the היכל heichal
itself. But not שחיטת קדשי קדשים, shchitat kodshei kodashim, yes.
Uh, the initial question about from a place where a non-כהן kohen
may stand. So how was the, how does that?
Does that's telling to expand. Don't say the מנחה mincha has to
be only in this corner, the southwest corner, it can be anywhere
because the פסוק pasuk where the non-כהן kohen stands tells you it
can be anywhere. Okay, it's to expand, it's not to limit. Okay.
Okay, so now
we compared it to a מנחה, mincha, and now we're going to
also compare, again, there's like I said, you know, this is done
a lot for the sake of contrast, we're going to compare the
normal story of קדשים, kodashim, whatever, to an עוף, of, a bird
sacrifice. חטאת העוף. Chatat ha'of. Now חטאת, chatat, the way you know
it by birds is that it's the reverse of
the
animals, okay, the mammals, which is the mammals, the חטאת chatat is
the only thing above and everything else is below, and the birds
it's the reverse. Okay, so the bird חטאת chatat is below. חטאת
העוף היתה נעשית על קרן דרומית מערבית. Chatat ha'of hayta na'aseit al
keren dromit maaravit. That gear to this corner, okay, that's again this
idea of לפני ה' פני המזבח, lifnei Hashem pnei hamizbeach, the same
way the מנחה mincha is done at that corner, right, that's also
where the bird sacrifice is done. Okay, על קרן דרומית מערבית ובכל
מקום היתה כשרה ואלא שזו היתה מקומה. al keren dromit maaravit uv'chol
makom hayta ksheira v'ela shezo hayta mekomah.
That's a strange משנה. Mishna. It says you know really it could
be anywhere, but this is where they did it. Which sounds like
it's לכתחילה. l'chatchila. Technically do it anywhere, but this was the designated
place. But the גמרא's Gemara going to read that otherwise. Okay, it's
a strange articulation. Okay. ובשלשה דברים היתה עושה כמין משמשת מלמטה ובשלשה
מלמעלה. U'v'shlosha dvarim hayta osa k'min mshameshet milmata uv'shlosha milmala.
That southwest corner was used for three things above, three things below.
Okay, מלמטה, milmata, what did they do below? חטאת העוף, Chatat ha'of,
and חטאת העוף v'chatat ha'of and הגשות. hagashot. That's what we, that's
what we spoke about a second ago: the touching of the מנחה
mincha to the corner, okay, the שחיטה shechita of the חטאת העוף,
chatat ha'of, and
שיירי הדם, shiyurei hadam, and that's where they would spill the remnant
of the blood, right, because remember it came down from doing the
חטאת chatat or wherever they did it and then they poured the
blood right over here, especially, okay,
so, one minute, okay, let me just look back here. Right, okay,
שיירי הדם, shiyurei hadam, they would spill it at the base over
here. ומלמעלה U'milmala and above, right here at the top where there
was like the
horn... ניסוך היין והמים, Nisuch hayayin vehamayim, that's where they would do
the pouring of the libations of the wine, the water you might
remember השיתין, Hashitin, that the גמרא Gemara talked exactly, that they expanded
it right this side and this side, they expanded it in order
to include the השיתין hashitin below here, so that's where they did
it at that corner and then the wine went down and then
went into the השיתין hashitin below.
Okay.
ניסוך היין והמים Nisuch hayayin vehamayim and עולת העוף Olat ha'of and
so the חטאת העוף Chatat ha'of was below, the עולת העוף Olat
ha'of was the same corner above. כשהיא רבה במזרח, K'she-hi rabba bamizrach,
but that's only when there was too much business in the east.
So normally they would do the עולת העוף Olat ha'of here, the
southeast, but if that got too busy they would move it to
the southwest.
כל העולים למזבח עולים דרך ימין, Kol ha'olim lamizbe'ach, olim derech yamin,
anybody who would go up to the altar would go up on
the right, all traffic please drive you know stay to the right,
okay, ומקיפין ויורדים דרך שמאל. Umakifin veyordim derech smol. So you go
up, you'd constantly you'd go counterclockwise, you'd make your turns to the
right, this is of course how we take out the ארון Aron
and how the ספר תורה, Sefer Torah, the ברכה Bracha is supposed
to move, we always turn to the right, and then you would
come back down, you'd come down on the left side of the
ramp, I mean the left side of the, meaning you'd come down
on your right, okay, right, because you're always moving you're always on
the right, traffic stays to the right, but anyway but if you're
looking straight at the altar you're going up on the right of
the ramp and coming down on the left.
Okay. חוץ מן העולה לג' אלו, Chutz min ha'oleh legimmel elu, except
for somebody going up for these three things, the ניסוך המים והיין,
Nisuch hamayim vehayayin, okay, because then it would be crazy, you'd have
to go all the way around like a series of one-way streets
right where if you could just turn you'd be there right away,
so here you're allowed to go against traffic. Okay. So here if
you have to go to the southwest corner because of like the
ניסוך המים והיין, Nisuch hamayim vehayayin, you could make an you'd go
up and
make an immediate left.
Okay. חוץ מן העולה לג' אלו Chutz min ha'oleh legimmel elu שיהיו
עולים ויורדים על העקב, she-yihyu olim veyordim al ha-akev, they would go
up and then you would sort of retract yourself, okay, and go
back down essentially the way you came. It sounds like you'd actually
walk backwards which would be dangerous, it could just mean that you
sort of go back the way you came.
Okay, let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. Okay. Okay, מנא
הני מילי, Minani mili, where's this from?
Okay, where's this from
that the חטאת העוף Chatat ha'of would be in the southwest corner?
All right. Where are we? אמר רבי יהושע אמר קרא, Amar Rabbi
Yehoshua amar kra, לא ישים עליה שמן ולא יתן עליה לבונה, lo
yasim aleha shemen velo yiten aleha levona, this is about a מנחה
Mincha that was brought for the קרבן עולה ויורד, Korban oleh veyored,
that type of a חטאת Chatat that you can bring of a
less expensive offering if you didn't have the money. So first you
would go from like a sheep or whatever then you'd go to
a bird and then you'd go to a מנחה Mincha and the
מנחה Mincha is like a מנחת חטאת. Minchat chatat. Okay, it's like
a sin offering מנחה. Mincha. Okay, so therefore מנחת חוטא Minchat chote
I should say, not a חטאת, Chatat, מנחת חוטא. Minchat chote. So
what does the verse say? לא ישים עליה שמן, Lo yasim aleha
shemen, do not put on it oil ולא יתן עליה לבונה velo
yiten aleha levona or frankincense כי חטאת היא, ki chatat hi, it's
a חטאת, Chatat, this מנחה. Mincha. חטאת קריה מנחה מנחה קריה חטאת.
Chatat karia mincha, mincha karia chatat.
There's this identification that a מנחה Mincha is like a חטאת, Chatat,
חטאת Chatat is like a מנחה, Mincha, or is a מנחה. Mincha.
מה חטאת טעונה צפון אף מנחה טעונה צפון. Ma chatat te'una tzafon,
af mincha te'una tzafon. So the first comparison is they both need
to be in the north. Now רש"י Rashi says and you'll see
there's a huge תוספות, Tosafot, רש"י Rashi says this makes absolutely no
sense because a bird חטאת Chatat doesn't have to be in the
north and a מנחה Mincha doesn't have to be in the north.
So what do you mean? This has to be in the north
and that has to be in the north? And even if it
means an animal חטאת Chatat has to be in the north, it's
not talking about the bird example. But רש"י Rashi says there is
no evidence, I mean you know the whole point that we're saying
here is that the מנחה Mincha is done over there. Okay. So
רש"י, Rashi, just as you want to look at רש"י, Rashi, מה
חטאת טעונה צפון Ma chatat te'una tzafon about eight lines after the
גמרא Gemara begins, יודע אני שגירסא זו שיבוש. yode'a ani she-girsa zu
shibush. I know this text is corrupted. I don't know what the
right text is, but I know that this text is corrupted.
Usually if he knew what the right one it would be corrected
in our text.
Yeah exactly. And רש"י Rashi is going to say at the end
he's going to speculate what a possible emendation is but they didn't
fix it in the text itself because it was clear רש"י Rashi
was just saying it like you know in case you strive to
fix it.
Okay. שיבוש הרי לא חטאת עוף ולא מנחה טעונה צפון. shibush, harei
lo chatat of velo mincha te'una tzafon. Neither of them are in
the north. ואם תאמר מנחת חוטא חלוקה מן השאר, Ve'im tomar minchat
chote chaluka min hashar, maybe normal מנחות Minchot are the southwest, maybe
a מנחת חוטא Minchat chote is the north because of
this? ולחטאת
בהמה מקיש לו, U-l'chatat behema makish lo, so we can solve both
problems. The link is not to a חטאת העוף, Chatat ha'of, the
link is to a generic חטאת, Chatat, and maybe this מנחה Mincha
is in the north but not other מנחות. Menachot. So that solves
both problems. A bird חטאת Chatat southwest. Normal מנחה Mincha southwest. But
a מנחת חוטא Minchat chote maybe that's the north. That was a
possibility. Okay.
ולחטאת בהמה מקיש לה הוי ליה למיסמך מתניתין Vel'chatat behema makish lo,
havei l'mi-m'smakh matnissin דקתני לעיל המנחות נקמצות בכל מקום בעזרה חוץ ממנחת
חוטא. de-katani le'al ha-menachot nikmatzot bechol makom ba'azara chutz miminchat chote. So
if that's true that there's a מנחת חוטא Minchat chote is in
the north, something should have said it! Our משניות, Mishnayot, which are
all devoted to telling you where you do these acts, right, should
have said that. We've... ever found anywhere that a מנחת חוטא minchas
chotei is in the north. Okay. So, and then he's about to
says da da da. So anyways, רש״י Rashi tries to switch the
gears for two. So, מה חטאת פסולה שלא לשמה אף מנחה פסולה
שלא לשמה. ma chatas psulah shelo lishmah af minchah psulah shelo lishmah.
Okay, so that was he had to find something. Okay, but תוספות
Tosfos has this huge discussion. Are we supposed to read this גמרא
Gemara that a מנחת חוטא minchas chotei is the north, even though
it goes against or the silence sort of silence of all the
other sources? Or do we just switch the גרסא girsa to say
something like, oh, a מנחה שלא לשמה minchah shelo lishmah was invalid.
Okay, so that's the first line of that, which is a big
question mark. But now we continue because that still isn't our answer
about how we know that a normal מנחה minchah is the southwest.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: Or a normal or
excuse me, or a normal חטאת העוף chatas ha-of is the southwest.
Okay. ומה מנחה u-mah minchah okay, ומה מנחה u-mah minchah so this
is where we're going to get the second part. So first we
got this curious north statement, which maybe it means about the about
the מנחת חוטא. minchas chotei. But now we're going to get it
to teach us about the חטאת העוף chatas ha-of is the southwest
because remember, the חטאת chatas it's being compared to here is a
חטאת העוף. chatas ha-of. This is in the context of the עולה
ויורד. oleh ve-yored. Okay, so ומה
מנחה בקרן מערבית דרומית u-mah minchah be-keren ma'aravit dromit and in the
same way the מנחה minchah is the southwest, which we said earlier
but we have yet to prove. So we're going to prove that
in a minute. אף חטאת בקרן מערבית דרומית af chatas be-keren ma'aravit
dromit so the bird חטאת chatas is southwest. Okay, so now we've
made the statement: the מנחה minchah and the bird חטאת chatas are
linked. The מנחה minchah southwest, bird חטאת chatas is southwest, sound like
the name of an airline.
Okay, thinking about Olly North, we were talking about the north, we
got southwest. Anyway, fine. עולה Oleh North. Anyway, עולה Oleh North. Okay,
anyway, ha ha, that's actually good. Anyway, so how do you know,
so we got the מנחה minchah and bird חטאת chatas linked southwest,
but we got to learn that the מנחה minchah itself is southwest.
How do you know that from?
So, okay, ומנחה גופא מנלן u-minchah gufa minah lan and how do
you know it true about the מנחה minchah itself?
דתניא di-tanya we learn in a ברייתא: baraisa: לפני השם. lifnei Hashem.
It says by the מנחה minchah this is what I said before.
Okay. הקרב אותה בני אהרן לפני השם, hikreiv osah bnei Aharon lifnei
Hashem, bring it before God, the מנחה. minchah. So the bringing we're
understanding to mean brings means touch it to the altar. But לפני
השם, lifnei Hashem, so לפני השם lifnei Hashem would mean the west
of the altar, the part facing the אוהל מועד. ohel moed. Okay,
that's לפני השם lifnei Hashem במערב. be-ma'arav. So that must mean the
west.
תלמוד לומר talmud lomar but another verse says אל פני המזבח, el
pnei ha-mizbe'ach, touch it to the face of the altar. And the
face presumably is where the ramp goes up. So הא כיצד? ha
keitzad? How do you do both? מגישה בקרן מערבית דרומית כנגד חודה
של קרן ודיו. magishah be-keren ma'aravit dromit kineged chudah shel keren ve-dayo.
You put it towards the southwest corner by right by the the
point of the corner and that's sufficient. Now what does it mean
that's sufficient? So you could say that's sufficient means you don't have
to do one at the south and one at the west, you
do it at the southwest. But the other thing a different גמרא
Gemara says is ודיו ve-dayo means you don't have to actually touch
the flour to the altar. It's enough to touch the vessel, even
though it says you should touch it or bring it before God.
So we're reading the word bring it to mean touch the altar.
And because of לפני השם lifnei Hashem and אל פני המזבח, el
pnei ha-mizbe'ach, we get that to be the southwest. That's true about
the הגשה hagashah of a מנחה. minchah. Okay, so remember, the הגשה
hagashah of the מנחה minchah takes place in the southwest. The קמיצה
kemitzah can take place anywhere. Okay, so that's as far as the
מנחה minchah is concerned.
As for how it worked, they'd be מגיש magish it and then
they would take it, they would touch it, and of course the
easy thing is to do the קמיצה kemitzah right there. But for
whatever reason they went somewhere else and they did the קמיצה, kemitzah,
it would be כשר kosher of course one imagines they 99% of
the time they do the קמיצה kemitzah right there. And then what
happened after that? They'd take it. They would take it up to
the altar and they'd burn it on the altar, right? They'd burn
the קמיצה kemitzah on the fire of the altar. And the bird
would be the חטאת העוף chatas ha-of would also be now done
at this corner, although what's going to be done by the חטאת
העוף? chatas ha-of? The שחיטה? shechitah? The blood? Exactly what? Because here
the קמיצה kemitzah wasn't done here, just the הגשה hagashah was done
here. So we'll see what was done by the bird in a
minute. Okay.
ודיו. ve-dayo. רבי אליעזר אומר: Rabbi Eliezer omer: יכול יגישנה למערבה של
קרן או לדרומה של קרן. yachol yagishenah le-ma'aravah shel keren o le-daromah
shel keren. Wait, maybe you should do it you know you could
do it not this corner, maybe you should do it either the
west or the you know or the south. אמרת. amarta. No. כל
מקום שאתה מוצא שני מקראות. kol makom she-atah motzei shnei mikra'os. Oh,
there are two verses. One says אל פני המזבח el pnei ha-mizbe'ach
and the other says לפני השם. lifnei Hashem. אחד מקיים עצמו ומקיים
חבירו. echad mekayem atzmo u-mekayem chaveiro. If you did it at the
corner you would exactly at the point you'd satisfy both verses. It
would both be
the לפני השם lifnei Hashem and אל פני המזבח. el pnei ha-mizbe'ach.
ואחד ve-echad and the other way of doing it if you just
read the verse to mean just one, okay, if you emphasize one
verse over the other מקיים עצמו ומבטל חבירו. mekayem atzmo u-mevatel chaveiro.
So you could emphasize one verse, but that would force you to
you sort of like bracket the other verse. So I would much
rather have a read that allows me to say both verses are
satisfied than to sort of you know privilege one verse over the
other. מניחין זה שמקיים עצמו ומבטל חבירו, menichin zeh she-mekayem atzmo u-mevatel
chaveiro, you ignore the read that allows that tells you focus on
one verse and ignore the other.
So anyway,
so therefore, so therefore you got to do it at the corner.
So now,
one minute.
So
אמר רב אשי כסבר האי תנא, amar Rav Ashi kasavar hai tana,
this תנא, tana, and I'm trying to figure out which תנא tana
he means.
They say שנו shanu רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer here.
The תנא tana רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is of the opinion.
That's what's in parentheses. That's the Artscroll's opinion. This תנא tana רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer maintains.
Okay, כולי מזבח בצפון קאי. kulei mizbeach batzafon kai. It's all in
the north. I just want to see what it's doing, I'm not
just sure which point it's explaining. Okay with this, because here's the
point. He says there actually is a way that you can actually
do it, I'm just not at the point of the corner, but
just at that one face and get both of them. Why? Because
if the entire altar is in the is in the north, right?
So if the entire altar is in the north, that means that
half of the door of the היכל heichal is
here,
right, if the entire altar is in the north. So therefore, if
half of the door of the היכל heichal is there, okay whatever
anyway you get the idea. Then when you're right here at the
south face, that's פני המזבח pnei hamizbeach even if you're not at
the corner, you're just at the south face and it's לפני השם
lifnei Hashem because there is it's directly opposite the door, right? So
it's not at a wall that's opposite the door, but where you
are it's opposite the door. So I get that point, I just
don't get which opinion it's trying to explain because both opinions said
the southwest corner. So it's possible you could have read the verse
that the that the south would have been enough. How is it
explaining it? Let me see what it says. Let's look at the
תנא. tana.
And here's the diagram.
Yeah, the diagram I know.
Oh oh I
see
because I oh oh oh.
One minute. Oh okay, I misread it,
I misread it. Okay, here's the way he was saying. He was
actually saying the following. Let's do it again. Okay, he was actually
saying let's read the רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer again. רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer wasn't saying you either way only gets you one. He was
actually saying if you emphasize the verse of the south, you actually
satisfy both verses. If you emphasize the verse of the west, you
don't satisfy both, but if you emphasize the verse of the south,
you satisfy both. Let's read that again. Okay, רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi
Eliezer omer, יכול יקישנו למערבה של קרן או לדרומה של קרן, yachol
yakishenu lema'arava shel keren o ledaroma shel keren, meaning not one or
the it's not one or the other, it's the corner. No, which
one should I do? That's how he reads it. You're not going
to do it at the corner. Should you do it at the
west or should you do it at the south? אמרת, amarta, well
here's your choice. כל מקום שאתה מוצא שני מקראות אחד מקיים עצמו
ומקיים חברו, kol makom she'ata motzei shenei mikra'ot echad mekayem atzmo umekayem
chavero, if you satisfied one you would satisfy, you know, the other.
ואחד מקיים עצמו ומבטל חברו, ve'echad mekayem atzmo umvatel chavero, but if
you go if you choose A, you really get A and B,
but if you choose B, you only get B. In that case,
מניחין את זה שמקיים עצמו ומבטל חברו, manichin et ze shemekayem atzmo
umvatel chavero, don't choose the verse that only satisfies itself and ignore
the other one. תופסין את זה שמקיים עצמו ומקיים חברו. tofsin et
ze shemekayem atzmo umekayem chavero. So do the one that gets you
both. So one of those sides, south or west, not the corner,
will actually satisfy both requirements. Which one will satisfy both requirements? Okay,
כשתאמר פני השם במערב, keshetomar pnei Hashem bama'arav, if you would have
just said the west, היכן קיימת פני המזבח? heichan kiyamta pnei hamizbeach?
Okay, so so if you had just did the west, it wouldn't
have been פני המזבח. pnei hamizbeach. So you can't say the west,
rather it is not the corner, it is the south. וכשתאמר פני
המזבח בדרום, ukeshetomar pnei hamizbeach bedarom, קיימת לפני השם, kiyamta lifnei Hashem,
period.
That's what I got wrong. The period. So he says, look, I'm
not going to say the corner, the point. No, you can do
just the south and that only not only gives you פני המזבח,
pnei hamizbeach, it even gives you also לפני השם. lifnei Hashem. The
south also gives you in front of the היכל. heichal. So then
the גמרא Gemara says, בדרום היכן קיימת? bedarom heichan kiyamta? How did
the south get you, now this is the גמרא Gemara talking. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says, בדרום היכן קיימת? bedarom heichan kiyamta?
How in the south did you get the לפני השם? lifnei Hashem?
Or peer or maybe לפני השם בדרום היכן קיימת? lifnei Hashem bedarom
heichan kiyamta? Anyway, how did you get the לפני השם lifnei Hashem
if you're on the south? So אמר רב אשי האי תנא סבר
כולי מזבח בצפון קאי. amar Rav Ashi hai tana savar kulei mizbeach
batzafon kai. The whole altar is in the north and you touch
it on the south face, the south face is both פני המזבח
pnei hamizbeach and לפני ה'. lifnei Hashem. Okay, that's פשט. pshat.
That's a weird, to say that היכן קיימת heichan kayamta is the
question of the גמרא Gemara is a weird read. It's
a...
yeah, but clearly what's going on.
I mean, I
guess that's the
way רש"י Rashi understands it.
I thought maybe somehow רב אשי Rav Ashi could be referring to
the צפון tzafon issue of the תנא. Tanna. Yeah, I don't think
so.
No, this is clearly the right read. Otherwise, anyway, that's why ר'
אלעזר Reb Elazar is saying something different than the תנא קמא. Tanna
Kamma. Okay. Now, let's get to the next line of the משנה,
Mishnah, which is this cryptic line. It said, you did it in
the southwest corner, and you could really do it anywhere, but this
is where you would do it. בכל מקום היתה כשרה. bechol makom
hayta kesheira. מאי קאמר? mai ka'amar? What does that mean?
אמר רב אשי, amar Rav Ashi, הכי קאמר: hachi ka'amar: בכל מקום
היתה כשרה למליקתה, bechol makom hayta kesheira limlikatah, אלא זהו מקומה להזאתה.
ela zehu mekoma lehazatah. And now we get an interesting parallel to
the מנחה. Mincha. The מליקה, Melika, the severing of the neck, you
could do anywhere. But the actual, you know, squirting of the blood,
that would be there. Okay, so it's similar to, you know, it's
similar to the מנחה. Mincha. Now, ironically, the מנחה Mincha is exactly
conceptually, right, the מנחה Mincha is a little bit, the order's reversed.
Because we try to make everything parallel to the ארבע עבודות. Arba
Avodos. You know, שחיטה shchita is the קמיצה. kmitza. הולכה holacha is
the- putting it in the כלי kli is the קבלה. kabala. הולכה
holacha is the הולכה, holacha, and putting it on the altar is
like the זריקה. zrika. Okay, but if you think about it, a
normal animal has two parts: the blood goes on the side of
the altar and the entrails go on the altar. The מנחה, Mincha,
you've got the מנחה Mincha going on the altar. What's going on
the side? Nothing. So you know what's going on the side? The
הגשה. hagasha. This idea that we read in the verse, which is
also not clear in the verse, it just says, you know, והקריבה,
vehikriva, but anyway we're reading הגשה, hagasha, that's like the throwing of
the blood on the side of the altar. It's actually interesting. Right,
although the actual- it's out of order. Because first you do the
הגשה, hagasha, then you do the קמיצה, kmitza, right? So you know,
the קמיצה kmitza which is like the שחיטה, shchita, so it were,
so it doesn't all work. But anyway, but now it works very
nicely, the parallel. Because the קמיצה kmitza can be done anywhere, and
the הגשה hagasha is done at this corner. And by the bird,
the שחיטה, shchita, the מליקה melika can be done anywhere, but the
הזאה, haza, the blood that hits the altar is done at this
corner. Okay? So the stuff that goes on the wall of this
altar, whether it's the touching or whether it's the blood, that's the
southwest. The severing, as it were, that could be anywhere. So it's
exactly parallel. Okay. תנינא להא דתנו
רבנן. tanina leha detanu rabbanan.
We've taught in a- we've taught in our משנה Mishnah what the
רבנן Rabbanan teach in a ברייתא. Braita. מליקה בכל מקום במזבח כשרה,
melika bechol makom bamizbeach kesheira, if you do the מליקה melika anywhere
on the altar it's כשר. kosher. Now is it anywhere in the
עזרה Azara or anywhere in the altar? Here it sounds like it's
anywhere in the- on the altar, okay.
So, הזיית דמה בכל מקום כשרה. hazayat dama bechol makom kesheira. Okay,
now, now again this is going to get confusing because we're- we're
expecting it to say, or we're wanting it to say, that even
though you can do the- the מליקה melika anywhere, you have to
do the squirting at the southwest, right? That's what we're claiming. But
now it's actually saying the squirting can be anywhere. But then it
goes on: הזייה ולא מיצה כשרה, hazaya velo mitza kesheira, if you
did the הזאה, haza, the squirting, and you didn't do the squeezing
out at the end, which is like the spilling of the שירים,
shirayim, that's כשר. kosher. ובלבד שיתן מכנגד הסובב ולמטה, uvilvad sheyiten mikeneged
hasovev ulemata, as long as you do it- דם הנפש- dam anafesh
as long as you do the squirting of the soul blood below
the- below the middle line. So מאי קאמר? mai ka'amar? What does
this say? Like, this is כשר, kosher, this is כשר... kosher... Okay,
this doesn't seem to, like, read well. It says the reason,
like, like anyway, so here's how the גמרא's Gemara going to read
it. הכי קאמר. hachi ka'amar. מליקה... melika...
so now, okay, so this ברייתא Braita supports our read of the
משנה Mishnah only if you edit the ברייתא. Braita. But here's how
we're going to edit the ברייתא. Braita. מליקה בכל מקום במזבח כשרה,
melika bechol makom bamizbeach kesheira, you could do the מליקה melika anywhere,
just like you could do the קמיצה kmitza anywhere. מיצת דמה בכל
מקום במזבח כשרה. mitzat dama bechol makom bamizbeach kesheira. We're going to
edit: it says if you squirted anywhere it's כשר, kosher, which is
not consistent with our משנה. Mishnah. So we're going to actually say,
no, no, no, the squirting, that has to be at the southwest
corner, but the squeezing out, which is like the שפיכת השירים, shfichat
hashirayim, that can be anywhere. Why? שכן אם הזה ולא מיצה כשר,
shekein im hiza velo mitza kasher, because if you did
the-
just the הזאה, haza, not the squirting, and not the squeezing, it's
כשר kosher the same way if you didn't do the spilling of
the שירים shirayim it's כשר. kosher. So therefore since if you didn't
do it with the squeezing out, it's כשר, kosher, so that's not
מעכב. me'akev. So therefore clearly, presumably, it's not going to be- it's
not going to be מעכב me'akev where you do it. Now that's
not necessarily a good argument because you could- if the spilling of
the שירים shirayim is not מעכב me'akev by, you know, a normal
mammal, you- you know, קרבן, korban, but you're supposed to do it
in a particular place on the base if you're going to do
it. Okay, but here... It’s start saying since the squeezing out, which
is like the שיריים, shirayim, is not מעכב, me'akev, therefore you can
do it anywhere on the altar. ובלבד שתהא מחוט הסיקרא ולמטה מדם
הנפש u'vilvad she'tehei mi'chut ha'sikra u'lemata mi'dam hanefesh as long as when
you actually do, not the squeezing out, but the squirting, which is
the actual of the blood, that is going from the, that is
actually from the soul blood of the animal, okay, that's the thing
that counts. So basically we edited this ברייתא braita to say again,
both in the משנה mishna and the ברייתא braita it does not
sound like the place you do the הזאה haza'ah is מעכב. me'akev.
It sounds like you prefer the southwest corner, but it's not that
important. The sound is that it's not מעכב, me'akev, and the גמרא
gemara reads it to say no, no, no, no, the מליקה melika
can be anywhere, the מיצוי mitzuy of the דם, dam, which is
like the spilling of the שיריים, shirayim, that can be anywhere, but
the הזאה, haza'ah, that has to be done דוקא davka at the
southwest corner, that's at least how the גמרא gemara is reading the
משנה mishna and the ברייתא. braita.
Okay, so what's דם
הנפש?
dam
hanefesh? What? דם הנפש dam hanefesh like the soul blood, like the
initial squirting out, the גמרא gemara assumes like what you're חייב כרת
chayav kares for.
Oh, not a place, sorry. Of the, of the.
Yeah.